Guide to the Three Rivers Second Nature Project Records, 1948-2005 AIS.2006.19B
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Three Rivers Second Nature Project Records
1948-2005
2000-2004
ULS Archives & Special Collections
STUDIO for Creative Inquiry
AIS.2006.19B
10.33 Linear Feet (16 boxes and 3 map folders)
The Three Rivers Second Nature Project took place between 2000 and 2005 with the goal of addressing the meaning, form, and function of public space and nature in Allegheny County, Pennsylvania. The project was directed by Reiko Goto and Tim Collins at Carnegie Mellon University's STUDIO for Creative Inquiry. The collection contains material that documents the streams and sub-watersheds of the Ohio, Monongahela, and Allegheny rivers.
History
The main goals of the Three Rivers Second Nature Project were to conduct a green infrastructure analysis, identify opportunities for ecological restoration, understand the history and basis for cultural restoration, and conduct public dialogue about the potential for all of the above. This project occurred between 2000 and 2005 under the direction of Tim Collins and Reiko Goto, who were fellows at Carnegie Mellon University's STUDIO for Creative Inquiry at the time.
This project was a second study by the STUDIO of Creative Inquiry into the relationship between nature and post-industrial public space. By assessing the status of the three rivers (Allegheny, Monongahela and Ohio) and fifty-three streams in the Three Rivers Second Nature Project area, the researchers and participants were able to establish an understanding about the current status of the waterways including, how polluted they were, what was causing it, how the rivers were being used, and how the rivers were effecting the surrounding natural environment. The next step was to see what possible steps could be taken to mitigate or even reverse the detrimental effects of human action and to open up dialogue on revitalizing the waterways for recreational use. The River Dialogues that took place included three sessions of the Monongahela Conference, which occurred between 2003 and 2005 and focused on the area's public space and its respective ecosystem as seen through art.
The two major actors in this project are Tim Collins and Reiko Goto. Tim Collins is an artist-research fellow at the STUDIO for Creative Inquiry at Carnegie Mellon University. His academic interests are focused around art and environmental change which can be seen in this project and, previously, in the Nine Mile Run Greenway Project, both of which he co-directed with Reiko Goto. Reiko Goto's academic interests focus on ecological art projects, which can encompass both redevelopment and installation works.
Scope and Content Notes
The STUDIO for Creative Inquiry Three Rivers Second Nature Project contains nine series entitled, Course Material, Data Collected, Funding Material, Meeting Minutes, Outreach Programs, Project Planning, References, Audio-Visual Material, and Maps. These series are housed in ten boxes and two flat-files and contain both textual and non-textual material.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Previous Citation
Three Rivers Second Nature Project Records, 2000-2005, AIS.2006.19B, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Arrangement
The collection is organized into nine series:
Series I. Course Material
Series II. Data Reports and Articles
Series III. Funding Material
Series IV. Meeting Minutes
Series V. Outreach Material
Series VI. Project Planning
Series VII. References
Series VIII. Audio-Visual Material
Series IX. Maps
Related Material
Nine Mile Run Greenway Project Records, 1945-2005, AIS.2006.19A, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Acquisition Information
Gift of The STUDIO of Creative Inquiry of Carnegie Mellon University in 2006.
Waterfronts -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Urban renewal -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Stream restoration -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Stream ecology -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Watersheds -- Pennsylvania; Rivers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Water -- Pollution -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Riparian restoration -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Land use, Urban -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Community development -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Greenways -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Rivers -- Economic aspects -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Rivers -- Recreational use -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Monongahela River Watershed (W. Va. and Pa.); Allegheny County (Pa.); Pittsburgh (Pa.); Negatives (Photographic); Slides (Photographs); Video recordings (physical artifacts); Floppy disks; Maps; Videocassettes; Minutes (Administrative records); Environment; Social action; Allegheny River Watershed (Pa. and N.Y.); Ohio River Watershed; Carnegie-Mellon University; Gotō, Reiko; Collins, Tim (Timothy M.); STUDIO for Creative Inquiry; Pennsylvania Environmental Council; Pennsylvania. Department of Environmental Protection; Brew House Association Inc; Andy Warhol Foundation for the Visual Arts; Americans for the Arts (Organization)
- Course material, 1996-2001; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains four folders of material related to two courses taught at Carnegie Mellon University. The courses were Design, Environment, and Economic Development, which was taught in 1996 by Frank Tugwell and Andrew McElwaine, and Grey Visions, Grey Infrastructure, which was taught in 2001 by Reiko Goto and Tim Collins.
  - Carnegie Mellon University "Design, Environment, and Economic Development" course material taught by Frank Tugwell and Andrew McElwaine, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Carnegie Mellon University "Grey Visions, Grey Infrastructure" course material taught by Reiko Goto and Tim Collins, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Data Reports and Articles, 1969-2004; II.
  This series contains 70 folders that contain data about the Three Rivers Second Nature locations either directly collected in the form of articles or published in reports by a variety of sources. These publications are predominately bound, however there are loose articles present; all articles and publications are named. Topics present in this series include water quality reports, land surveys, animal surveys, and park surveys. The information in this series spans 35 years from 1969 to 2004.
  - "Herr's Island Study: A Recreation Island for Pittsburgh and Allegheny County", By: The City of Pittsburgh, Department of City Planning, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "A Dendrochronologic Analysis of the Effects of Air Pollution on Tree Growth" By: Joan Dahl and William R. Griffith of Carnegie Mellon Univerity, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "The Relational Between Historical Air Pollution and Tree Growth in Pittsburgh, PA" By: Michell Small and Beryl Kravitz of Carnegie Mellon University, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Environmental Impact Final Report" By: U.S. Army Engineers, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - "Lower Monongahela River Navigation System Feasibility System Final Report" By: U.S. Army Engineers, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Water quality data, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Lower Monongahela River Navigation System Feasibility Study: Interim Report" By: U.S. Army Corp of Engineers Pittsburgh District, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Water quality data, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Alcosan CSO Evaluation Project: Water Quality Sampling Protocol Draft" By: Camp Dresser & McKee and L. Robert Kimball and Associates Inc., 1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Rouge River National Wet Weather Demonstration Project Technical Report" By: Razik Alsaigh, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Rouge River National Wet Weather Final Value Engineering Report" By: George Riek and Jeffrey Boerma, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Recreational Use Survey and Valuation of Recreational Use Types for Portions of the Allegheny, Monongahela, and Ohio Rivers" By: The Ohio Valley Sanitation Commission (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Water quality data, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Water quality data, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Water quality data, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Normandeau Associates Environmental Consultants Aquatic Resource Study, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Water quality data, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "Sheraden Park Site Analysis" By: Hanson Associated, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Water quality data, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Ohio River Ecosystem Restoration Program: Integrated Decision Document and Environmental Assessment" By: U.S. Army Corps of Engineers Great Lakes and Ohio Division, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "Daylighting: New Life for Buried Streams" By: Richard Pinkham of the Rocky Mountain Institute, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "Riverbank Conditions: Phase I Report" by: The STUDIO for Creative Inquiry, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "Water Quality: Phase I Executive Summary" by: The STUDIO for Creative inquiry, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "Water Quality: Phase I Report" by: The STUDIO for Creative Inquiry, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "Water Quality Report Phase I Executive Summary" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - "Three Rivers Second Nature" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - "Biotic Assessment" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "Riverbank Conditions Phase I Report" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - "Water Quality Phase I Report" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Water quality data, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Three Rivers Second Nature Aquatic Invertebrate Biological Assessments: Phase I Interim Report" by: Michael Koryak and Linda Stafford, U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Monongahela and Youghiogheny Rivers, Pools 2 and 3 Riverbank Geology, Conditions, and Access Reports" by: Roman Kyshakevych and Henry Prellwitz, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Stream Restoration and Daylighting Opportunities in the Pittsburgh Region: Phase I Report" by: Richard Pinkham, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Water quality data, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Three Rivers Second Nature History of Public Access" by: Steve Burnette, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Three Rivers Second Nature Vegetation Survey of the Monongahela River" by: Dr. Susan Kalisz, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Three Rivers Second Nature Stream Restoration and Daylighting Opportunities in the Pittsburgh Region: Phase II Draft" by: Richard Pinkham, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Three Rivers Second Nature Water Quality Report" by: Kathy Knauer, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Terrestrial Project Reports Phase II" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Social Project Reports Phase II" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Stream Restoration and Daylighting Phase I" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "Draft Report to the Technical Advisory Committee Phase II" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "Aquatic Project Reports Phase II" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "River Dialogues Project Data" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 15-18)
  - Statewide Fish Consumption Advisory, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "From Rivers to Lakes, Engineering Pittsburgh's Three Rivers" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "Study on Southwestern Pennsylvania's Wastewater and Water Quality Problems" by: National Research Council, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - "Battle of Homestead and Carrie Furnaces 6 and 7" by: National Park Service, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "Three Rivers Second Nature Aquatic Invertebrate Biological Assessments: Phase II Interim Report" by: U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "Aquatic Reports, Allegheny River" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Terrestrial Reports, Allegheny River" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "The Regionalization Report" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "The Monongahela Conference on Post Industrial Community Development" by: The STUDIO for Creative Inquiry, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Water quality data, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - "Stream Project: Report Outline", 2003 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - "Aquatic Invertebrate Biological Assessment Phase III" By: Army Corp of Engineers, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "Aquatic Project Reports Phase IV: By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - "Stream Project Reports Phase IV" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - "Terrestrial Project Reports of the Ohio River Phase IV" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Water quality data, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - "Physical Investigation of Hillsides: Preservation, Conservation, and Development Issues: Final Report Outline" by: Unattributed, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - "Where the Three Rivers Converge: Unassessed Waters and the Future of EPA's TMDL Program - A Case Study" by: William Luneburg, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - "An Ecological and Physical Investigation of Pittsburgh Hillsides Report to the City of Pittsburgh Hillsides Community" By: Stephen Farber, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 37-38)
  - "Three Rivers Second Nature Phase IV Report (on Water)" By: Rose Reilly, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - "Report on Water Quality Analysis" By: Ayat Osman, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "Sewered Streams Identification and Separation Strategies" By: Michael Baker Inc., Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "Three Rivers Second Nature Streambank Conditions" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Funding Material, 1994-2005; III.
  This series contains six folders that contain funding records such as grant applications, letters of award, and items created for funding applications. The organizations represented in this series include both national and local based funding agencies. The funding material present in this series spans ten years from 1994 to 2004.
  - Americans for the Arts, The Andy Warhol Foundation for the Visual Arts, Brew House Association Inc., Carnegie Mellon University, Department of Environmental Protection, and the Environmental Education Grant Program, 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Howard Heinz Endowment, 1994-2004 (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
  - McCune Foundation, National Science Foundation, and Pennsylvania Environmental Council, 2001-2003 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Pittsburgh Foundation, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Meeting Minutes, 2001-2003; IV.
  This series contains two folders arranged in chronological order by meeting date. The content of these folders includes meeting minutes and meeting agendas of citizens committees, advisory committees and other constituent gatherings.
  - Meeting Minutes, 1999-2002 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Meeting Minutes, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Outreach Programs, 2002-2005; V.
  This series represents the efforts the STUDIO for Creative Inquiry made to involve the public in its endeavor. Included are press releases, publicity and documents collected during organized gatherings called "River Dialogues." River Dialogues was a year-long series of community discussion surrounding the Three Rivers Second Nature project in 2003.
  - Press Releases and Articles, 2002-2005 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - River Dialogues, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 13-15)
- Project Planning, VI.
  This series contains five subseries that span 16 folders; the folders are arranged chronologically within each subseries.
  - Community Outreach Planning, 2000-2003; 1.
    This subseries contains one folder arranged in chronological order. Community outreach planning consists of records that discuss possible outreach activities, what the projected plan is for an activity, and directions for the leaders of community groups. This folder contains information from 2000 to 2003.
    - Community Outreach Planning, 2000-2003 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Executive Summaries and Vision Statement, 2000-2004; 2.
    This subseries contains one folder arranged in chronological order that records various executive summaries, Three Rivers Second Nature summaries, and a vision statement. This folder contains information from 2000 to 2004.
    - Executive Summaries and Vision Statement, 2000-2004 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Park Planning Material, 3.
    This subseries contains four folder arranged in chronological order that records the plans created for parks located in the Three Rivers Second Nature survey area. These folders range from 1997 to 2004.
    - "A New Partnerships Initiative for AMD Remediation and Community Enhancement" by: AMD & ART, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - "Master Plan: Inventory, Assessment, and Opportunities" by: LaQuatra Bonci Associates, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - "Pittsburgh Regional Parks Master Plan: Final Draft Recommendations" by: LaQuatra Bonci Associates and "Three Rives Park Design Handbook" by: Riverlife Task Force, 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Loose articles, 2001-2004 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - River Planning Material, 4.
    This subseries contains nine folders arranged in chronological order that record the plans created for each of the three rivers in Pittsburgh: the Monongahela, the Allegheny, and the Ohio. These folders range from 1993 to 2005.
    - "Main Plan Document Draft Copy" by: Chester environmental, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - "Youghiogheny River Conservation Plan: Preliminary Findings Report" by: Mackin Engineering Company, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - "Monongahela River Conservation Plan: Final Report" by: Mackin Engineering Company, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - "The Riverfront Development Plan: A Comprehensive Plan for the Three Rivers" by: Pittsburgh City Council, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - "Revealing River Potential, Clean Water is Second Nature" by: STUDIO for Creative Inquiry, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - "Three Rivers Conservation Plan Draft" by: Pennsylvania Environmental Council, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - "Pittsburgh's Neighborhoods Find the Rivers! A River Opportunity Plan" by: Community Partners Institute, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Loose articles, 2001-2004 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - "Pine Creek: Watershed Assessment Protection and Restoration Plan" by: The Pennsylvania Environmental Council, March 2005 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Stream Daylighting Material, 2000-2001; 5.
    This subseries contains one folder arranged in chronological order that records conversations and plans to daylight streams in the Three Rivers Second Nature survey area. Daylighting involves discovering streams or waterways that were covered over and removing the cover, this brings the stream back into the daylight. This folder ranges from 2000 to 2001.
    - Stream Daylighting Material, 2000-2001 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Teaching and Presentation Material, 2000; 6.
    This subseries contain one folder arranged in chronological order that records slides used for an educational presentation and ecology and environmental education modules that were created for seventh graders in an effort to teach them about urban waterways and brownfields. The modules were created in part by Reiko Goto. This folder only contains material from 2000.
    - Teaching and Presentation Material, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- References, VII.
  This series contains 77 folders arranged by type, loose articles, or bound publications, then in chronological order. This material records information that the Three Rivers Second Nature team referred to as they were planning and working on this project. The material collected was created by a variety of individuals including local, state, and federal entities. The folders range from 1948 to 2005.
  - Loose Articles, 1992-2002; 1.
    This subseries contains ten folders arranged in chronological order and ranging from 1992 to 2002. The information recorded in these articles includes information about clean waterways, river conservation, wildlife conservation, etc.
    - Loose Articles, 1992-2002 (Box 4, Folder 9-18)
  - Bound Publications, 2.
    This subseries contains 67 items arranged in chronological order and ranging from 1948 to 2005. These publications come from a variety of local, regional, state, and federal organizations and include material that was used as a reference during the planning and execution of the Three Rivers Second Nature Project.
    - "Ohio River Valley Water Sanitation Compact", 1948 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - "Ground-Water Resources of the Valley-Fill Deposits of Allegheny County, Pennsylvania" by: J. H. Adamson Jr., J. B. Graham, and N. H. Klein, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - "Aquatic Resources of the Ohio River" by: Ohio River Water Sanitation Commission, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - "Management of Urban Watersheds: The Potential Impact of Regulatory Action" by: Mitchell J. Small and William P. Darby, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - "An Evaluation of the Effects of Mainstem Navigation Dams on the Water Quality of the Upper Ohio River" by: U. S. Army Corps of Engineers, Pittsburgh District, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - "Monongahela River Navigation Projects Annual Water Quality Report" by: U. S. Army Corps of Engineers, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - "Guide to the availability of Hydrologic Data, Greater Pittsburgh Region, Pennsylvania" by: U. S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 76-352, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - "Implementing Stormwater Management in Allegheny County: A Training Manual" by: Allegheny County Department of Planning, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - "Remaking Cities: Proceedings of the 1988 International Conference in Pittsburgh" by: The Pittsburgh Chapter of the American Institute of Architects (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - "Water Quality Trends Ohio River and its Tributaries" by: Ohio River Valley Water Sanitation Commission, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - "A Casebook in Managing Rivers for Multiple Uses" by: Association of State Wetland Managers, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - "Assessment of ORSANCO Fish Population Data Using the Modified Index of Well Being" by: Ohio River Valley Sanitation Commission, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - "Water Quality Trends on Ohio River and its Tributaries 1980-1990: A Supplement to the 1977-1987 Study" by: Ohio River Valley Water Sanitation Commission, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - "Toxics Substances Control Program: Pittsburgh to Wheeling Field Study" by: Ohio River Valley Sanitation Commission, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - "Water Quality Trends Ohio River and its Tributaries: Organic Compounds, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - "Ground Water Studies of Neville Chemical Site Mile Point 6.2 of the Ohio River" by: Ohio River Valley Sanitation Commission, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - "Wetlands Guide to Science, Law, and Technology" by: Mark S. Dennison and James F. Berry, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - "Best Management Practices for Erosion Control During Trail Maintenance and Construction" by: State of New Hampshire, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - "What's a River Worth: A Valuation Survey of the Ohio River Corridor" by: Ohio River Valley Sanitation Commission, the National Park Service, and the Ohio River Basin Commission, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - "Municipal Authorities in Pennsylvania" by: Commonwealth of Pennsylvania Department of Community and Economic Development, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - "A Handbook of Constructed Wetlands" by: Luise Davis, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 7)